♪You crossed the sea of ​​stars and came with light♪
♪เธอข้ามผ่านหมู่ดวงดาว มาพร้อมกับแสงสว่าง♪
♪My heart is like the dust, and I couldn't bear to stain the hemline♪
♪หัวใจฉันเปรียบเหมือนฝุ่น ไม่อยากแปดเปื้อนกระโปรงของเธอ♪
♪To love in a different way, the fireworks are in the stars' good graces♪
♪ความรักที่ไม่เหมือนใคร ดอกไม้ไฟที่ดวงดาวยังชายตามอง♪
♪I turn around and realize that my heart is empty ♪
♪หันกลับมาจึงเข้าใจ ดวงใจได้ขาดหายไป♪
♪I miss the overflowing galaxy surging into the sea♪
♪ความคิดถึงท่วมท้นจักรวาล เอ่อล้นจนเต็มท้องทะเล♪
♪Even the fireworks desire to give the stars a future♪
♪ดอกไม้ไฟอยากเป็นที่พึ่งพิงให้ดวงดาว♪
♪As long as you are around♪
♪ขอเพียงแค่มีเธออยู่♪
♪Even the fireworks fear to bloom♪
♪ดอกไม้ไฟกลัวจะสว่างแล้วดับสูญ♪
♪Looking at you, the light in your eyes dimmed♪
♪มองดูนัยน์ตาของเธอ แสงไฟค่อย ๆ เลือนหาย♪
♪I laughed at myself and that I deserve it ♪
♪ทำได้แต่สมน้ำหน้าตัวเอง♪
♪My heart skips a beat, but I'm afraid I'm not worthy of the future that you desire♪
♪ฉันใจสั่น♪
=You Are My Glory=
=ดุจดวงดาวเกียรติยศ=
=Episode 19=
=ตอนที่ 19=
It's all you, Mr. Zhang.
ต้องพึ่งคุณจางแล้ว
You're exaggerating.
ไม่หรอกครับ ๆ
It's not bad.
แต่ว่าดีมากนะคะ
Just like your previous work.
เรื่องที่แล้วก็ออกมาดีมากเลยค่ะ
Thanks to you, Jingjing.
เรื่องนี้ต้องพึ่งจิงจิงต่างหาก
You performed well.
จิงจิงแสดงดี
That's why the sales are high.
ยอดขายตั๋วถึงได้ถล่มทลาย
No, no.
ไม่หรอกค่ะ
Congratulations, Jingjing.
ยินดีด้วยนะจิงจิง
Thank you.
ขอบคุณค่ะ
So humble.
ถ่อมตัวเกินไปแล้ว
Excuse me, gentlemen.
ทุกคน ขอตัวสักครู่ครับ
For you, Ms. Qiao.
สวัสดีครับ คุณเฉียว
It's delicious.
ชงออกมาใช้ได้เลย
Try it.
คุณลองสิครับ
Thank you.
ขอบคุณค่ะ
Ms. Wang.
สวัสดีครับ คุณวัง
Long time no see.
ไม่ได้พบกันนานนะครับ
What brought
คุณซู ทำไมวันนี้ถึงปลีกเวลา
you here, Mr. Su?
มาถึงที่นี่ได้
Last time I checked
เห็นโมเมนต์วีแชทของคุณ
your Moments, you were still in the UK.
ไม่กี่วันก่อนยังอยู่อังกฤษอยู่เลย
I've been abroad due to my work.
เพราะทำงานเลยต้องอยู่แต่ที่เมืองนอก
I just came back today.
วันนี้เพิ่งได้กลับประเทศ
And I made meeting you
พอกลับมา
my top priority once I came back.
ก็ตรงมาที่นี่ทันทีเลยครับ
I wonder
ก็ไม่รู้
who's the important one then.
ว่าเป็นใครที่ได้รับเกียรติขนาดนี้
Definitely not me.
แต่คงไม่ใช่ฉันแน่
All right. I'll leave you two alone.
เอาล่ะ พวกคุณคุยกันเถอะค่ะ
It's been a long time.
ไม่ได้เจอกันนานนะ
How are you?
สบายดีไหม
Not bad.
ก็พอได้อยู่ค่ะ
I can imagine.
ผมก็คิดว่าเป็นอย่างงั้น
You're all over
แค่เปิดโซเชียลขึ้นมา
the social media.
ก็เจอแต่ข่าวคุณทั้งนั้น
I highly doubt it.
ไม่ขนาดนั้นหรอกค่ะ
Perhaps because I
อาจจะเป็นเพราะ
always click on your news that
ผมกดดูข่าวคุณบ่อยเกิน
the algorithm recommends your content to me.
แอปมันเลยเด้งมาอัตโนมัติ
Thank you for supporting me then, Mr. Su.
ขอบคุณประธานซูที่ช่วยเพิ่มยอดวิวนะคะ
So who I saw
ที่แท้ครั้งก่อน
last time in your place
คนที่ผมเจอที่บ้านคุณ
is your high school classmate.
คือเพื่อนม.ปลายของคุณงั้นเหรอ
Can't believe you follow
ไม่คิดเลยว่าประธานซู
the gossips, Mr. Su.
จะดูข่าวกอสซิปด้วย
As I said,
ก็ผมเพิ่งบอกไปว่า
it's the algorithm.
กดเข้าไปดูบ่อย
But no, not this time.
แต่คราวนี้ไม่ใช่แบบนั้น
During the casual match
ครั้งก่อนที่คุณไปร่วมงาน
that you took part in,
แมตช์บันเทิงของเกม
I was at the scene.
ผมก็อยู่ที่นั่นด้วย
In the VIP room upstairs.
ที่ห้องวีไอพีชั้นบนน่ะ
I see.
อ้อ อย่างนี้นี่เอง
He played really well.
เขาเล่นเกมใช้ได้เลยนะ
A Tsinghua graduate.
จบจากมหาวิทยาลัยชิงหัวชื่อดัง
Was he
ผู้ชายแบบนี้
a lady-killer too
ตอนมัธยม
back in high school?
คงมีเสน่ห์ไม่เบา
Was he part of the reasons
ที่คุณบอกเลิกผม
why you broke up
แบบไม่มีเยื่อใยอย่างนั้น
with me so decisively?
เขาก็เป็นเหตุผลหนึ่งใช่ไหม
Who would have known that
คิดไม่ถึงเลยว่าประธานซู
Mr. Su lacks confidence in himself.
จะขาดความมั่นใจในตัวเองขนาดนี้
That's because you never
เพราะตอนที่คุณมองผม
looked at me the way you looked at him.
ไม่เคยมีสายตาแบบนั้นเลย
We shouldn't
ตอนนี้พวกเรา
dwell on this anymore.
ไม่ควรต้องมาพูดเรื่องพวกนี้กันอีกแล้ว
You're right.
ก็จริงนะ
After all,
คนเราน่ะ
we have to move on.
จะต้องมองไปข้างหน้าสิ
Mr. Su.
ประธานซู
I'll leave you be then, Mr. Su.
ประธานซู เชิญตามสบายนะคะ
I'll join my friend.
ฉันขอตัวไปหาเพื่อนก่อน
Hold on.
รอก่อน
One more thing.
ยังมีอีกเรื่องหนึ่ง
I just wanted to
ฉันต้องการที่จะมาขอบคุณ
thank you for your help, Mr. Su.
ที่ประธานซูช่วยไว้คราวก่อน
If you're occupied,
ถ้าคุณกำลังยุ่งอยู่
I'll gladly take my leave.
งั้นฉันไม่รบกวนแล้วดีกว่าค่ะ
You're welcome.
ยินดีครับ
It was just a small matter.
งานง่าย ๆ แค่นั้นเอง
I have always wanted
ความจริงมีเรื่องเรื่องหนึ่ง
to tell you this
ที่ผมอยากจะคุยกับคุณ
but I never had the chance to.
เพียงแต่ยังไม่มีโอกาส
The reason I went to your house last time
ครั้งก่อนที่ผมไปบ้านคุณ
was
ก็เพราะ
to apologize.
ต้องการจะขอโทษคุณ
That gameplay footage of yours
เรื่องคลิปที่คุณเล่นเกม
was leaked by my ex-girlfriend.
แฟนเก่าผมเป็นคนปล่อยเอง
Of course,
แน่นอนว่า
that's why she's
เธอก็เลยกลายเป็น
an
แฟนเก่า
ex-girlfriend now.
ของผม
You are in my WeChat
คุณอยู่ในวีแชทของฉัน
and both of you recorded my gameplay
พวกคุณเห็นคลิปที่ฉันเล่นเกม
before posting it online.
ก็เลยโพสต์ลงเว็บงั้นเหรอ
Not both of us.
ไม่ใช่พวกผม
Just me.
มีแค่ผมที่ดู
I enjoyed watching you
ผมเห็นว่าคลิปที่คุณเล่นเกม
play game.
ดูสนุกดี
So I recorded it.
เลยเซฟลงมือถือไว้
I didn't know
ผมก็ไม่รู้
how she had found out
ว่าแฟนเก่าผมเห็นได้ยังไง
copied it before posting it online.
เลยรีโพสต์คลิปลงเว็บ
I was careless.
ผมไม่ทันได้ระวังเอง
I'm sorry.
ขอโทษนะ
Mr. Su, someone like you
คนระดับอย่างประธานซู
never locked your own phone?
มือถือไม่ได้ล็อกรหัสเลยเหรอ
It was my fault.
ความผิด
An oversight.
ของผมเอง
My bad.
ที่สะเพร่าไม่ระวัง
I should have blocked you.
ฉันน่าจะบล็อกคุณไปตั้งนานแล้ว
I bet your girlfriend
ตอนนี้แฟนของคุณ
must be upset now.
คงจะเสียใจน่าดู
Do let your girlfriend know that,
ฉันฝากไปบอกเธอหน่อยนะ
thanks to her,
ขอบคุณในความหวังดี
my endorsement contract was renewed
ตอนนี้ฉันได้เป็นพรีเซนเตอร์เกม
for three more years.
ต่ออีกสามปี
Ex-girlfriend.
แฟนเก่า
I'm single now.
ตอนนี้ผมโสด
You performed really well.
คุณแสดงออกมาได้ดี
I'm impressed.
จนผมประทับใจเลยล่ะ
You flatter me.
ไม่ขนาดนั้นค่ะ
If I may, would you
ไม่รู้ว่า
give me the honor
คุณพอจะมีเวลา
to bring you out
ให้ผมได้เลี้ยง
for a dinner? Just to make things right.
เป็นการขอโทษอีกครั้งไหม
No need.
เรื่องนั้นไม่ต้องหรอกค่ะ
Everything is already over.
ยังไงเรื่องราวทั้งหมดก็คลี่คลายแล้ว
If there's nothing else for me, Mr. Su,
ถ้าประธานซูไม่มีอะไรแล้วละก็
I'll join my friend now.
ฉันจะไปหาเพื่อนฉันแล้วค่ะ
Wait.
รอก่อน
You mentioned that you were still
ครั้งก่อนตอนที่แข่งคุณพูดว่า
single in the match.
คุณยังโสด
Is it true?
จริงหรือเปล่า
If it is,
ถ้าเป็นความจริง
then,
งั้น
are you willing to
คุณเฉียวสนใจจะ
start a new relationship?
เริ่มต้นความรักครั้งใหม่ไหม
A new relationship
ผมหมายถึง
with someone you've known.
กับคนเดิมน่ะ
I have a question for you,
ฉันมีคำถามจะถามคุณ
Mr. Su.
ประธานซู
Go ahead.
ถามมาสิ
You said your girlfriend
คุณพูดว่าแฟนเก่าคุณ
had posted my video online.
เอาคลิปของฉันไปอัพลงเว็บ
Do you really feel sorry for me?
คุณรู้สึกเสียใจต่อฉันจริงเหรอ
Why do I feel like
ทำไมฉันรู้สึกว่า
you're enjoying it?
คุณดูภูมิใจล่ะ
Because someone wanted your attention so badly that
ภูมิใจที่มีคนหึงคุณ
she did this.
ถึงขนาดนี้
Maybe the word "enjoy" is not proper.
อ้อ พูดว่าภูมิใจไม่ได้สิ
It's more like you want to see
ต้องพูดว่า ใจจดใจจ่อดูว่าฉัน
how I will deal with the situation.
จะมีท่าทียังไงมากกว่า
You said you had gone to my house that day
คุณบอกว่าคุณแวะมาบ้านฉัน
to apologize.
เพื่อที่จะขอโทษ
But that was
แต่ว่าตอนนั้น
half a month
เรื่องก็ผ่านมาแล้ว
after the incident.
ตั้งครึ่งเดือนได้
It was more like you were nearby
คงจะบังเอิญผ่านมาพอดี
and on a whim,
แล้วดันนึกขึ้นได้
you came to apologize.
เลยแวะมาขอโทษซะหน่อย
Also,
แล้วอีกอย่าง
I won the match.
เพราะฉันแข่งชนะ
What if I had lost?
ถ้าฉันแพ้ล่ะ
What if I had lost so badly that
แพ้แบบเละเทะ
everyone was mocking me.
แพ้จนถูกชาวเน็ตหัวเราะเยาะ
Would you still be here
คุณจะยังยืนอยู่ตรงนี้
telling me all this?
พูดกับฉันแบบนี้ไหม
Also,
แล้วก็
I need to
ฉันขอตอบคำถาม
clarify something.
ที่คุณถามมาก่อน
I took our relationship
ตอนที่ฉันคบกับคุณ
seriously.
ฉันจริงจังมากนะ
The break-up
เพราะงั้นสาเหตุที่เลิก
had nothing to do with someone else.
ก็ไม่ได้เกี่ยวกับใครทั้งนั้น
Have you already forgotten
ส่วนสาเหตุที่เลิกกัน
why we broke up?
คุณลืมไปแล้วเหรอ
I have always been curious
ความจริงมีเรื่องหนึ่ง
about one thing.
ที่ฉันคาใจมาตลอด
When you asked me
ตอนที่คุณ
to give my career up,
เคยบอกให้ฉันออกจากวงการ
were you truly ready
คุณเตรียมพร้อม
to spend the rest of your life with me?
ที่จะแต่งงานกับฉันจริงเหรอ
I doubt it.
คงไม่หรอก
You said those words so nonchalantly.
คุณก็แค่พูดขึ้นมาลอย ๆ
That was when I realized that
ตอนนั้นฉันก็คิด
you'd never ever
ว่าคุณคงไม่วางฉัน
viewed me as your equal.
ไว้ที่ระดับเดียวกับคุณหรอก
Even until now.
ที่จริงตอนนี้ก็ยังเหมือนเดิม
You're always on your high horse.
คุณเอาแต่คิดว่าตัวเองสูงส่ง
I can't deal with it.
ฉันถึงรับไม่ได้
Mr. Su,
ประธานซู
we belong in different worlds.
พวกเราไม่เหมาะสมกันหรอก
Did Su Ye bother you again?
ซูเหย่มาเต๊าะเธออีกแล้วเหรอ
Listen to me.
ฉันบอกเธอไว้เลยนะ
Do not ever
เธอห้ามไปหลงเชื่อ
believe his sweet promises.
คำหวานที่หลอกลวงนั่น
He
คนอย่างเขานะ
has a cute face
หน้าตาก็ถือว่าหล่ออยู่
but his personality
แต่นิสัยนะ
doesn't hold a candle to Mr. Yu's.
เทียบอาจารย์อวี๋ไม่ได้แม้แต่ปลายเล็บ
Have you
ช่วงนี้เธอ
talked to Mr. Yu lately?
ได้ติดต่ออาจารย์อวี๋บ้างไหม
You guys
มือถือของฉัน
confiscated my phone most of the time.
ก็ฝากไว้ที่พวกพี่แทบจะตลอดเวลา
What do you think?
พี่ดูสิมีไหม
You're right.
นั่นสินะ
You didn't even have the time
แค่เวลาจะนอน
to sleep.
เธอยังไม่มีเลย
Won't you be back
แต่สองวันนี้
in Shanghai within the next two days?
เธอกลับเซี่ยงไฮ้แล้วไม่ใช่เหรอ
When you're free,
ถ้าเธอพอมีเวลา
invite him out for a dinner.
ก็เลี้ยงข้าวอาจารย์อวี๋หน่อยสิ
He couldn't attend the celebratory dinner last time.
ครั้งก่อนที่พวกเราฉลองกันเขาก็ไม่มา
We still owe him one.
ถือว่าชดเชยแล้วกัน
Wait, no.
คงไม่ได้สินะ
Tomorrow is the reunion dinner.
พรุ่งนี้เป็นวันสิ้นปีแล้ว [*ในที่นี้คือวันก่อนตรุษจีนหนึ่งวัน]
He might have been in his hometown already.
อาจารย์อวี๋คงจะกลับไปหาพ่อแม่แล้ว
Maybe after the Spring Festival?
ไว้หลังตรุษจีน
Wait, no!
ไม่สิ
Mr. Yu and you are from the same town, right?
เธอกับเขาอยู่บ้านเกิดเดียวกันนี่
You can invite him out back in your hometown.
ไปเลี้ยงข้าวเขาที่บ้านเกิดก็ได้
Aren't you going back
หลังจากงานแสดงวันชูอี [วันชูอี : วันชิวอิก วันตรุษจีน]
straight away
จบแล้ว
after your performance on the first day of the lunar new year?
เธอจะตรงกลับอี๋ซิงเลยไหม
So this is why
พี่มาหาฉันดึกดื่น
you called me for in the middle of the night?
เพราะเรื่องนี้เหรอ
Of course not.
ไม่ใช่สักหน่อย
I need to brief you
ฉันจะมาคุยรายละเอียด
about the event on the first day of the lunar new year.
เรื่องงานเลี้ยงวันชูอีกับเธอ
Where is she?
ไปไหนแล้วล่ะ
Xiao Zhu!
เสี่ยวจู
I was checking the mail.
ฉันไปดูตู้จดหมายมา
We have a lot of letters.
จดหมายเยอะมากเลย
Okay.
อื้ม
They're all bank reconciliations.
บิลที่ธนาคารส่งมาทั้งนั้นเลย
Jingjing.
จิงจิง
Someone wrote a letter to you.
มีคนเขียนจดหมายมาหาเธอด้วย
Several letters to you.
ตั้งหลายฉบับแน่ะ
Look.
เธอลองดูสิ
(Ms. Qiao, Zhongshan South Street, Huangpu District, Shanghai, China)
(ผู้รับ คุณเฉียว เลขที่ A2801 อ้าวเจียง 1 ถนนจงซานหนานอี เขตหวงผู่ เซี่ยงไฮ้ ผู้ส่ง อวี๋)
(Jingjing.)
(จิงจิง)
(I hope all is well.)
(เธอสบายดีนะ)
(I went back to Yixing earlier this month)
(เดือนก่อนฉันกลับมาอี๋ซิง)
(and I found our chat history)
(เปิดเจอบทสนทนา)
(on my old computer.)
(ในคอมพิวเตอร์เก่าน่ะ)
(You asked me a lot of questions)
(เธอถามคำถามฉันเยอะเลย)
(but I replied to you)
(แต่ว่าฉันในตอนนั้น)
(rudely.)
(ทำตัวเสียมารยาทไปหน่อย)
(And now,)
(ตอนนี้อยากจะถามว่า)
(I know my answers)
(เวลาก็ผ่านมานานแล้ว)
(are long overdue, but can I give them to you now?)
(เธอยังอยากฟังคำตอบจากฉันไหม)
(Your first question was about)
(คำถามแรกของเธอ)
(the escape velocity)
(เกี่ยวกับยานอวกาศจะหลุดพ้นจากโลก)
(required for a spacecraft.)
(ต้องใช้ความเร็วเท่าไหร่)
(Can I come to ask you)
(วันหลังถ้ามีคำถาม)
(when I have questions in the future?)
(ฉันขอถามคุณได้ไหมคะ)
(I'm just a beginner.)
(ที่จริงฉันเป็นพวกหน้าใหม่)
(I've only just started.)
(เพิ่งจะเริ่มสนใจเอง)
(Sure.)
(ได้ครับ)
What should I ask?
(ฉันจะพูดอะไรดีนะ)
Chang'e...
(ฉางเอ๋อ)
(One question.)
(มีคำถามหนึ่ง)
(How fast should a space probe travel)
(ยานสำรวจต้องใช้ความเร็วเท่าไหร่)
(to escape the Earth's gravity?)
(ถึงจะพ้นจากแรงดึงดูดของโลกคะ)
(The answer is on Baidu.)
(คำถามนี้คุณเสิร์ชหาเอาเองได้)
(You guys were discussing the technological difference)
(ฉันเห็นที่พวกคุณคุยกันในกระทู้)
(between the Chinese and the USA aerospace technology.)
(เรื่องเทคโนโลยีอวกาศ ของอเมริกากับจีนยังต่างกัน)
(Is the gap that huge?)
(พวกเรากับพวกเขา)
(The discussion in the forum is so lively!)
(ในกลุ่มคุยกันสนุกจัง)
(Do you think we can)
(คุณคิดว่ามนุษย์จะสามารถ)
(migrate to Mars one day?)
(ย้ายไปอยู่ดาวอังคารได้จริง ๆ ไหม)
Ignored again...
ไม่ตอบอีกแล้ว
When will you ever
เมื่อไหร่ถึงจะเริ่ม
talk to me?
คุยกับฉันก่อนบ้างเนี่ย
(Your first question was about)
(คำถามข้อแรกของเธอ)
(the escape velocity)
(เกี่ยวกับเรื่องความเร็วของยานอวกาศ)
(required for a spacecraft.)
(ที่ต้องการหลุดพ้นจากแรงโน้มถ่วงโลก)
(If I remember correctly,)
(ถ้าฉันจำไม่ผิด)
(The three cosmic velocities)
(ความเร็วสูงสุดของจักรวาล)
(are)
(น่าจะเป็น)
(within the syllabus of high school physics.)
(เนื้อหาวิชาฟิสิกส์ตอนม.ปลาย)
(Did you not pay attention)
(ตอนเธอเข้าเรียน)
(during class?)
(ไม่ได้ตั้งใจฟังเลยใช่ไหม)
(I drew a simple graph)
(เพื่อให้เธอเข้าใจ)
(Escape Earth's gravity) (to help you understand it.)
(ฉันจะวาดแผนผังคร่าว ๆ)
(These are)
(ด้านบนคือ)
(the definitions of the three cosmic velocities)
(นิยามเรื่องความเร็วสูงสุดของจักรวาล)
(as well as their principles.)
(และหลักการคำนวณ)
(You asked this question)
(แต่ตอนที่เธอถามคำถามนี้)
(due to Chang'e 1.)
(ก็เพราะดาวเทียมฉางเอ๋อหนึ่ง)
(It's different)
(มันแตกต่างออกไป)
(because the Moon is the Earth's satellite.)
(ดวงจันทร์เป็นดาวบริวารของโลก)
(It is affected)
(ตัวมันเอง)
(by the Earth's gravity.)
(ได้รับผลกระทบจากแรงดึงดูดของโลก)
(The velocity required)
(ดังนั้นยานสำรวจ)
(for a probe)
(จึงกลายเป็นบริวารของดวงจันทร์)
(to reach the Moon)
(ความเร็วหลุดพ้นที่ต้องการ)
(is lower than the second cosmic velocity.)
(จึงน้อยกว่า 11.2 กิโลเมตรต่อวินาที)
(Take Chang'e 1 for example,)
(ยกตัวอย่าง ดาวเทียมฉางเอ๋อหนึ่ง)
(as the)
(ถูกจำกัด)
(payload capacity of a rocket back then was limited,)
(ด้วยแรงส่งของจรวด)
(Chang'e 1 first entered)
(ดาวเทียมฉางเอ๋อหนึ่งเข้าสู่)
(the Earth's elliptic orbit.)
(วงโคจรรูปวงรีของโลก)
(It then adjusted its velocity several times)
(แล้วจึงใช้แรงขับของตัวมัน)
(through its own force)
(ปรับความเร็วอยู่หลายครั้ง)
(before)
(สุดท้าย)
(entering the lunar transfer orbit)
(ออกจากวงโคจรโลกเพื่อทำวิถีสู่ดวงจันทร์)
(at the speed of)
(ด้วยความเร็ว)
(10.58km/s.)
(10.58 กิโลเมตรต่อวินาที)
(Today's letter)
(เนื้อหาของจดหมายวันนี้)
(is a bit boring.)
(อาจจะน่าเบื่อหน่อยนะ)
(I don't know if you'll finish reading it.)
(ไม่รู้ว่าเธอจะตั้งใจอ่านจนจบไหม)
(However, the letter tomorrow)
(แต่ว่าเนื้อหาของพรุ่งนี้)
(will be more fun.)
(จะสนุกขึ้นมาบ้าง)
(Take care.)
(ขอให้สุขภาพแข็งแรงนะ)
(Yu Tu)
(อวี๋ถู)
(Jingjing.)
(จิงจิง)
(I hope all is well.)
(เธอสบายดีนะ)
(Blizzard in the south today)
(วันนี้ทางใต้หิมะตกหนัก)
(so I decided to walk back home.)
(ฉันเลยเดินกลับบ้านแทน)
(I thought)
(ตลอดทาง)
(about your question on the way.)
(ก็นึกถึงแต่คำถามของเธอ)
(The gap between our and the US aerospace)
(ความแตกต่างระหว่าง ยานอวกาศของจีนกับอเมริกา)
(is too vast a subject.)
(คำถามนี้กว้างเกินไปหน่อย)
(I might need)
(ฉันอาจจะต้อง)
(a lot of letters to explain it to you.)
(เขียนจดหมายหลายฉบับเพื่อตอบเธอ)
(In this letter, let's talk about)
(จดหมายฉบับนี้พวกเรามาพูดถึง)
(the modern history of aerospace.)
(ประวัติศาสตร์การพัฒนา ยานอวกาศในปัจจุบัน)
(To be frank,)
(ปฏิเสธไม่ได้ว่า)
(in terms of aerospace,)
(ในด้านการบินและอวกาศ)
(we are still)
(ของเรากับประเทศที่เป็น)
(quite far from)
(ระดับสูงสุดของโลก)
(the world's best.)
(ยังถือว่าห่างไกลกันนัก)
(Sometimes when we talk about this)
(บางครั้งคุยกับเพื่อนร่วมงาน)
(among my colleagues,)
(ถึงเรื่องนี้ทีไร)
(some feel down.)
(ก็มีบางคนที่ท้อใจ)
(They said there was at least a 30- or 40-year gap.)
(ที่ว่าอย่างน้อย ต้องใช้เวลาสามสิบสี่สิบปี)
(However,)
(แต่ระยะห่างสามสิบสี่สิบปีนี้)
(that)
(ไม่ได้แปลว่า)
(doesn't mean we need 30 or 40 years more.)
(ต้องใช้เวลาเท่านี้ถึงจะตามทันได้)
(It's part of the reasons why my colleagues)
(นี่คือส่วนหนึ่งที่ฉัน)
(and I)
(กับเพื่อนร่วมงาน)
(work so hard.)
(กำลังทุ่มเททำกัน)
(I've talked)
(การเปรียบเทียบระหว่างจรวด)
(about the comparison between human spaceflight)
(กับยานอวกาศที่บรรทุกคนได้)
(and the rocket.)
(ก็ได้พูดไปแล้ว)
(Tomorrow, we can talk about)
(พรุ่งนี้ค่อยมาพูดกัน)
(deep space probes.)
(เรื่องการสำรวจอวกาศ)
(It's my forté.)
(นี่คือเรื่องที่ฉันถนัด)
(The Voyager)
(ยานวอยเอจเจอร์)
(and the Jade Rabbit)
(รถอวี้ทู่ของเรา)
(have a romantic backstory.)
(นั้นเป็นเรื่องที่โรแมนติกมาก)
(That said, based on the post delivery speed,)
(แต่ความเร็วของไปรษณีย์)
(you'll most likely receive it after the lunar new year.)
(คงส่งไปหาเธอไม่ทันก่อนช่วงตรุษจีนแน่)
(Jingjing.)
(จิงจิง)
(Will you return to Yixing)
(วันตรุษจีน)
(during the lunar new year?)
(เธอกลับอี๋ซิงไหม)
Time flies.
เวลาผ่านไปไวมากเลย
The third year is about to end soon.
อีกแป๊บก็จะจบปีสามแล้ว
Jingjing,
จิงจิง
what do you want to do
หลังเรียนจบ
after graduation?
เธอตั้งใจจะทำอะไรเหรอ
Are you sending out your CV?
เตรียมยื่นเรซูเม่หรือยัง
Not yet.
ยังเลย
Someone is asking me to star in a film.
แต่มีคนชวนฉันไปถ่ายหนังล่ะ
A film?
ถ่ายหนังเหรอ
That's great!
ฟังดูน่าสนุกจัง
Do it!
เธอไปถ่ายเลย ไปถ่ายเลย
Oh, Jingjing.
อ้อใช่ จิงจิง
Are you in a relationship?
เธอมีแฟนหรือยังนะ
No.
ไม่มี
Well,
คือว่า
I heard...
ก่อนหน้านี้ได้ยินมาเรื่องหนึ่ง
That's what they said.
พวกเขาพูดกันว่า
Yu Tu
อวี๋ถู
and Xia Qing are together now.
คบกับเซี่ยฉิงแล้วล่ะ
♪I dreamed of starlight pulling the sleeves♪
♪ฉันฝันเห็นแสงดาวระยิบระยับ บนชายแขนเสื้อ♪
(Add photo to recycle bin?)
(ลบ)
♪A white top covering the thin shoulders♪
♪ชุดสีขาว ปกคลุมหัวไหล่อันซูบเซียว♪
♪I have seen the wounds healed with each passing year♪
♪ฉันเห็นกาลเวลาเยียวยาบาดแผลได้♪
♪There will always be people♪
♪อย่างไรก็มีคนไล่ตามชั่วฟ้าดินสลาย♪
(No file selected)
♪เคยรักเธอ มองไปยังดาวทอประกายบนฟากฟ้า นัยน์ตาที่สงบนิ่ง♪
♪And I loved the universe in your heart♪
(ประวัติสนทนากับอวี๋ถู)
(Delete all chat history?)
(ลบประวัติสนทนา)
(Yes)
♪กาลเวลาไม่เคยหยุดรอ เก็บซ่อนความเสียใจในสิ่งที่ทำไปตลอดเวลา♪
(Delete all chat history?)
(ลบประวัติสนทนา)
♪The wind passes by the tall buildings with no one awaiting it♪
♪ลมพัดผ่านตึกสูง ไม่มีใครเฝ้ารออีกต่อไป♪
♪I've dreamed of traveling around the planet♪
♪ฉันก็เคยคิดฝันท่องไปตามดวงดาว♪
♪Seeing the galaxy pass through the clouds♪
♪ผ่านมวลเมฆ ดูทางช้างเผือกที่หลั่งไหล♪
♪I looked at the hills with sorrow♪
♪ฉันเคยมองขุนเขาอย่างเศร้าหมอง♪
(I'm here.) (Your idol is here.)
♪ทางออกแห่งฝัน อยู่ที่สุดขอบทะเลดาวหรือไม่♪
♪Looking into the distance♪
♪เฝ้ามองว่าดาวดวงไหนคือนัยน์ตาเธอ♪
♪The wind sings the song of freedom♪
♪สายลมขับร้องอิสรภาพ ฉันตั้งใจฟังความอ่อนโยนของกาลเวลา♪
(Thank you for your answers.)
(ขอบคุณสำหรับคำตอบนะ)
(However,)
(แต่ว่า)
(it doesn't matter anymore.)
(มันไม่มีความหมายกับฉันอีกแล้ว)
(Chinese New Year's Eve)
(วันสิ้นปี) [*วันก่อนตรุษจีน]
Why did you put
ทำไมคุณถึง
the beef here?
เอาเนื้อวัวมาด้วยล่ะ
We can't finish it.
มันกินไม่ได้แล้ว
We will leave tomorrow morning.
พรุ่งนี้เช้าพวกเราก็จะไปแล้ว
Jingjing is not a big eater.
จิงจิงก็คงไม่กิน
A reunion dinner is supposed to be a feast.
อาหารคืนข้ามปีจะน้อยได้ยังไง
Having some leftovers brings good luck.
ต้องกินเหลือสิถึงจะดี
Superstition!
งมงาย
Pipe down.
เบา ๆ หน่อยคุณ
Jingjing is sleeping.
จิงจิงหลับอยู่
You're awake.
ตื่นแล้วเหรอ
We didn't want to wake you up.
ไม่กล้าปลุกลูกน่ะ
What's the matter?
เป็นอะไรไปลูก
Why are you getting all chummy with me?
อยู่ ๆ ก็มาอ้อนแม่
For no reason.
เปล่าค่ะ
My, my.
คุณดูสิ
Can't you see?
คุณก็พูดแปลก
Who else can your daughter be all chummy with
ลูกสาวไม่อ้อนคุณ
other than with her own mother?
แล้วจะให้ไปอ้อนใครล่ะ
Are you hungry, Jingjing?
หิวแล้วใช่ไหม จิงจิง
What did you make for me?
ทำอะไรให้หนูกินคะเนี่ย
Wait! It's hot.
อย่า อย่า มันร้อน มันร้อน
Ouch!
ร้อนจังเลย
Did you burn yourself?
โดนลวกหรือเปล่าลูก
Are you okay?
ไม่เป็นอะไรใช่ไหม
I'm fine.
ไม่ค่ะ ไม่
Silly girl.
ดูลูกคนนี้สิ
Here.
อะ นี่
You sure you guys don't want to
พ่อแม่ไม่รอ
head back together with me tomorrow night?
กลับพร้อมหนูคืนพรุ่งนี้เหรอคะ
My performance will be done
การแสดงของหนู
at around 8PM.
น่าจะจบประมาณสองทุ่มกว่า
It's our turn
ตรุษจีนปีนี้
to hold the new year gathering.
ถึงตาบ้านเราเป็นเจ้าภาพแล้ว
We need to go back early to prepare for it.
ต้องรีบกลับไปเตรียมตัวน่ะลูก
Then I should have gone back today
รู้งี้หนูกลับบ้าน
to have the reunion dinner with you guys.
ไปกินข้าวข้ามปีดีกว่า
Traveling back and forth is so time-consuming.
อย่างงี้พ่อแม่ก็ต้องเทียวไปเทียวมาแย่เลย
Don't worry. We are free.
แม่กับพ่อมีเวลาว่างน่ะลูก
You have a performance.
ลูกต้องร่วมแสดงอีก
If you got stuck in the traffic,
ถ้าเกิดรถติดเข้า
that'd be a problem.
จะแย่เอานะ
Okay then.
ก็ได้ค่ะ
Come.
มา ๆ
A toast to our daughter.
อวยพรให้จิงจิงลูกสาวของเรา
Hope you will become prettier
สวยวันสวยคืนนะลูก
and will find a husband
รีบหาลูกเขยดี ๆ
soon.
มาให้พ่อกับแม่ได้แล้วนะ
I wish both of you good health too.
ขอให้พ่อกับแม่สุขภาพร่างกายแข็งแรงนะคะ
Okay.
จ้ะ
You take care too.
ดูแลสุขภาพด้วยนะลูก
Don't work too much.
อย่าหักโหมมาก
A husband?
ลูกเขยที่ดีน่ะ
She is not in a hurry.
ไม่ต้องเร่งรัดให้ลูกหาไว ๆ หรอก
People in her field marry late.
อาชีพนักแสดง แต่งงานช้าก็ไม่เป็นไร
Don't stress her out.
อย่าไปกดดันลูกเลย
Since it's the reunion dinner,
นาน ๆ จะถึงวันข้ามปี
eat more.
ลูกกินเยอะ ๆ หน่อย
Here.
มา
Come.
เร็ว ๆ
You have to.
ต้องกินเยอะ ๆ
Stop giving me food, mom.
แม่คะ ไม่ต้องตักแล้ว
I have a show tomorrow.
พรุ่งนี้มีแสดง
I can't eat this much.
กินเยอะขนาดนี้ไม่ได้ค่ะ
But it's tomorrow night, isn't it?
พรุ่งนี้ลูกแสดงตั้งมืดไม่ใช่เหรอ
Just don't eat so much during the day.
ตอนกลางวันก็อดข้าวเอาสิ
Come.
มา มา มา
Look at you.
ดูคุณสิ
Say something nice at least.
คุณต้องพูดคำที่เป็นมงคลหน่อย
Don't eat so much?
เอาแต่พูดว่าอดอยู่ได้
No one should starve during the first day of the lunar new year.
วันชูอจะอดได้ยังไง
You're jinxing her.
คุณพูดปัดลางดีออกไปหมดแล้ว
Your dad
ลูกดูพ่อลูก
is becoming superstitious.
ยิ่งแก่ยิ่งงมงาย
Look at his logic.
พูดเรื่องงมงายออกมาฉอด ๆ เชียว
How is it superstitious?
งมงายที่ไหนกัน
Your favorite.
ลูกชอบกินอันนี้
For you.
ให้ลูก
Eat more.
ต้องกินเยอะ ๆ นะ
Dad!
พ่อคะ
It's too much.
เยอะเกินไปแล้ว
Eat more.
กินเข้าไปเยอะ ๆ
Come.
มา มา มา
Cheers.
พวกเรามาชนแก้วกัน
Sure.
มา
Happy new year!
สุขสันต์วันตรุษจีน
(Yu Tu)
(ไม่มีข้อความใหม่จากอวี๋ถู)
(It doesn't matter anymore.)
(มันไม่มีความหมายกับฉันอีกแล้ว)
Mom,
แม่คะ
drive safe, okay?
เดินทางระมัดระวังนะคะ
Yes.
รู้แล้วลูก
After you're done,
การแสดงของลูกจบแล้ว
when will you arrive?
จะกลับบ้านเมื่อไหร่ล่ะ
I'm the first to perform
หนูแสดงเป็นอันดับแรก
so before midnight.
คงถึงบ้านไม่ถึงเที่ยงคืนค่ะ
I will wait for you while watching TV then.
พวกเราจะดูทีวีรอลูกนะ
Okay.
ได้ค่ะ
We'll go now.
ไปแล้วนะลูก
Take care.
เดินทางดี ๆ ค่ะ
Bye, uncle, auntie.
คุณอาคุณน้าไว้พบกันใหม่นะคะ
Bye.
ไว้เจอกัน ๆ
I'll take care of Jingjing!
หนูจะดูแลจิงจิงเองค่ะ
Good.
-โอเค
Come forward, please.
ขยับมาข้างหน้าหน่อยค่ะ
Let's welcome our opening guest,
(เพนกวินเทเลวิชั่น) ขอเชิญพบกับแขกรับเชิญคนแรก
Qiao Jingjing.
เฉียวจิงจิง
(Penguin TV Chinese New Year Countdown Event)
(งานฉลองส่งท้ายปีเก่า)
(Green room)
(โซนพักผ่อน)
Here, Ms. Qiao.
มา คุณเฉียว เชิญทางนี้ครับ
No need to see us off.
คุณไม่ต้องไปส่งพวกฉันหรอก
Go do your thing.
ไปทำธุระเถอะ
Happy new year.
สุขสันต์วันตรุษจีนนะคะ
(Penguin TV Chinese New Year Countdown Event)
(งานฉลองส่งท้ายปีเก่า ออกอากาศทั่วโลก)
Why are you so happy?
ทำไมเธอถึงดีอกดีใจขนาดนี้ล่ะ
Nothing.
ไม่มีอะไรสักหน่อย
Thank you.
ขอบคุณค่ะ
Since you're going to Yixing,
เธอจะกลับอี๋ซิง
let's carpool.
ฉันขอติดรถไปด้วยสิ
When did he
เขาโทรหาเธอ
call you?
ตอนไหนเนี่ย
Yesterday afternoon.
เมื่อวานตอนบ่าย
Let's go.
พวกเราไปกันเถอะ
No need.
เธอไม่ต้องไปหรอก
Stay here
อยู่เป็นเพื่อน
and keep your mom company.
แม่เธอที่นี่เถอะ
It's okay.
ไม่เป็นไรหรอก
I already told my mom.
ฉันบอกแม่ไปแล้ว
I'll come back here
เดี๋ยวพรุ่งนี้ฉันกับคนขับรถ
with the driver tomorrow.
กลับมาด้วยกันก็ได้
I guess I won't follow then.
งั้นฉันไม่ไปแล้วดีกว่า
Pack your stuff then.
เธอเก็บของเองทีไร
But you always forget this and that...
ชอบลืมนู่นลืมนี่ตลอด
Mr. Wang,
พี่โชเฟอร์
no need to be our chauffeur.
ไม่ต้องไปส่งพวกเราหรอก
I'll drive.
เดี๋ยวฉันขับเอง
You have a driver's license?
นายมีใบขับขี่เหรอ
Of course.
มีสิ
Sometimes, my work requires me
บางครั้งงานของพวกเรา
to visit some
ต้องไปตรวจสอบนอกสถานที่
extreme environments
ที่สภาพแวดล้อมไม่ค่อยดี
like the desert or the snowfield.
อย่างทะเลทราย หิมะหนา
Been there, done that.
ฉันขับมาหมดแล้ว
Highway is just a piece of cake.
เพราะงั้นถนนปกติน่ะ
Don't worry.
เธอวางใจได้
My driver's license.
ใบขับขี่ของฉัน
(Driver's License)
(ใบอนุญาตขับขี่รถยนต์)
Jingjing.
จิงจิง
Can you help me with the navigation?
ช่วยเปิดเนวิเกเตอร์หน่อย
You don't even know the way.
นายไม่รู้ทาง
Why be the driver then?
แล้วจะไปแย่งงานคนขับทำไม
Why are you here?
ทำไมนายมาอยู่ที่นี่ได้ล่ะ
You don't need to visit your parents?
ไม่กลับบ้านไปฉลองตรุษจีนเหรอ
I came from Yixing this morning.
ตอนเช้าฉันมาจากอี๋ซิง
If there had been no reunion dinner yesterday,
ถ้าเมื่อวานไม่ใช่วันสิ้นปี
I would have been here since yesterday.
ฉันคงมาตั้งแต่เมื่อวานแล้ว
Jingjing.
จิงจิง
Your reply scared me.
ฉันมีเรื่องร้อนใจ
I'll take a nap.
ฉันของีบแป๊บนะ
Okay.
ก็ได้
(Driver's License, Yu Tu)
(อวี๋ถู)
I need to fill the car up.
ฉันจะเติมน้ำมันหน่อย
I'll go to the toilet.
ฉันไปเข้าห้องน้ำหน่อย
Okay.
โอเค
It's late night.
มันดึกแล้ว
I worry about you.
ไม่ค่อยวางใจ
Okay.
อืม
So my answers truly don't matter anymore?
มันไม่มีความหมายแล้วจริง ๆ เหรอ
♪I dreamed of starlight pulling the sleeves♪
♪ฉันฝันเห็นแสงดาวระยิบระยับ บนชายแขนเสื้อ♪
♪A white top covering the thin shoulders♪
♪ชุดสีขาว ปกคลุมหัวไหล่อันซูบเซียว♪
♪I have seen the wounds healed with each passing year♪
♪ฉันเห็นกาลเวลาเยียวยาบาดแผลได้♪
♪There will always be people running towards eternity♪
♪อย่างไรก็มีคนไล่ตามชั่วฟ้าดินสลาย♪
♪The bustling intersection♪
♪ท่ามกลางทางแยกผู้คนพลุกพล่าน♪
♪Looking back all of a sudden under the dim light♪
♪แสงไฟริบหรี่ เหลียวหลังมองไป♪
♪I loved your eyes looking at the starry sky♪
♪เคยรักเธอ มองไปยังดาวทอประกายบนฟากฟ้า นัยน์ตาที่สงบนิ่ง♪
♪And I loved the universe in your heart♪
♪ก็เคยรักเธอ ในใจฉันเธอคือทุกอย่าง ในจักรวาล♪
♪Time does not stop, remember the time that we failed to treasure♪
♪กาลเวลาไม่เคยหยุดรอ เก็บซ่อนความเสียใจในสิ่งที่ทำไปตลอดเวลา♪
♪The wind passes by the tall buildings with no one awaiting it♪
♪ลมพัดผ่านตึกสูง ไม่มีใครเฝ้ารออีกต่อไป♪
♪I've dreamed of traveling around the planet♪
♪ฉันก็เคยคิดฝันท่องไปตามดวงดาว♪
♪Seeing the galaxy pass through the clouds♪
♪ผ่านมวลเมฆ ดูทางช้างเผือกที่หลั่งไหล♪
♪I looked at the hills with sorrow♪
♪ฉันเคยมองขุนเขาอย่างเศร้าหมอง♪
♪Will the exit of the dream lead to the end of the starry sky?♪
♪ทางออกแห่งฝัน อยู่ที่สุดขอบทะเลดาวหรือไม่♪
♪Looking back all of a sudden♪
♪เหลียวหลังมองไป♪
♪Which galaxy am I drifting on?♪
♪ฉันล่องลอยอยู่บนทะเลดาวสายไหนกัน♪
♪Looking into the distance, which of the stars are your eyes?♪
♪เฝ้ามองว่าดาวดวงไหนคือนัยน์ตาเธอ♪
♪It's out of reach, so dazzling and hard to get♪
♪ดาวระยิบระยับ เอื้อมไม่ถึงครอบครองไม่ได้♪
♪Time does not hold back, the spring and autumn in the passing time♪
♪กาลเวลาไม่รอใคร เมื่อเวลาผ่าน สรรพสิ่งก็เปลี่ยนไป อดีตจบสิ้นลง♪
♪The wind sings the song of freedom as I listen to the tenderness of time♪
♪สายลมขับร้องอิสรภาพ ฉันตั้งใจฟังความอ่อนโยนของกาลเวลา♪